<article
	 xmlns:omg="http://www.omegahat.org"
	 xmlns:c="http://www.C.org"
	 xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
	 xmlns:sh="http://www.shell.org">

<title>Compiling and Calling Routines for XPath from R and LLVM</title>
<author>
  <firstname>Duncan</firstname>  <surname>Temple Lang</surname>
  <affiliation>UC Davis</affiliation>
</author>

<para>
Consider an artificial example to start.
We have an XML document  of the form
<xml:code><![CDATA[
<doc>
<value>1</value>
<value>2</value>
<value>3</value>
...
<value>300</value>
</doc>
]]></xml:code>
We want to identify the <xml:tag>value</xml:tag> elements
for which the value of the fibonacci function is greater than 10
when we call the fibonacci function with the content of the <xml:tag>value</xml:tag> element.
In other words, we want to
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>  
  get the value of each <xml:tag>value</xml:tag> as a number
</listitem>
<listitem>
  pass it in a call to fib()
</listitem>
<listitem>
  determine if the result is greater than 10
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
We could do this in R by extracting all of the <xml:tag>value</xml:tag> nodes
and then extracting their values and computing the  fibonacci number for each
then filtering the nodes based on those values.
</para>

<para>
We implement the fibonacci routine in C with
<c:code><![CDATA[
int
fib(int n)
{
    if(n < 2)
	return(n);
    
    return(fib(n-1) + fib(n-2));
}
]]></c:code>
</para>


<para>
The XPath interface cannot call this routine directly.
Instead, we need to marshall the values from the XPath expression to the native C types
when calling the routine and returning its value.
So we would write a little wrapper routine that expects the XPath expression to have provided a number
in the call
<c:code>
void
xpathFib(xmlXPathParserContextPtr ctxt, int nargs)
{
    float num = xmlXPathPopNumber(ctxt);
    int val = fib((int) num);
    xmlXPathReturnNumber(ctxt, val);
}
</c:code>
We compile these two routines into a shared library/DSO
which we can load into R to make the symbols accessible to R.
</para>
<para>
We can then use this in our R XPath calls.
We first load the XML package, and the newly  created DSO and then
get the address of the <c:func>xpathFib</c:func> routine:
<c:code>
library(XML)
dyn.load("fib.so")
fib.ptr = getNativeSymbolInfo('xpathFib')$address
</c:code>
</para>


<para>
Now we can use this xpathFib routine in a call to getNodeSet(), xpathSApply(), xpathApply(), etc.
via the <r:arg>xpathFuns</r:arg> parameter.  We provide a list of named elements,
with the names being those to use in the XPath expression, and the value being
the address of a native routine or an R function.
</para>
<para>
So we can filter our <xml:tag>value</xml:tag> nodes in place with
<c:code>
doc = xmlParse("doc.xml")
cc = getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = fib.ptr))  
</c:code>
</para>


<section>
<title>LLVM</title>

<para>
  Now that we have seen how we could make the fibonacci routine available to XPath
  in C, we will mimic this using LLVM.
  We will not discuss how we generated the LLVM version of fib and xpathFib.
  That is discussed in the LLVM compilation chapter and package.
  For now, we can just take a short-cut and convert the fib.c C file we wrote into IR with
<sh:code>
clang -emit-llvm -S -O2 fib.c -o fib.ll `xml2-config --cflags`
</sh:code>
</para>


<para>
We want to do essentially the analogous steps we did for the C code.
We want to load the xpathFib routine. We load the Rllvm package
and parse the fib.ll module.
<r:code>
library(Rllvm)
m = parseIR("fib.ll")
</r:code>
When we created the .so, we linked the compiled C code with the libxml2 library.
However, here we haven't done a linking step. So we have references in our
xpathFib routine to routines xmlXPathPopNumber, xmlXPathNewFloat and valuePush
that are in libxml2. These are available via the XML.so from the XML R package.
So we can find the addresses of these and provide them to LLVM to essentially do the linking:
<r:code>
llvmAddSymbol("xmlXPathPopNumber", "xmlXPathNewFloat", "valuePush")
</r:code>  
</para>


<para>
  Again, since we haven't explicitly linked code, we have to provide LLVM with a run-time engine or context.
<r:code>
ee = ExecutionEngine(m)
</r:code>
As we did with the C code, we get the address of the xpathFib routine, but this time in the LLVM module:
<r:code>
llfib.ptr = getPointerToFunction(m$xpathFib, ee)@ref
</r:code>
We can pass this routine address via the <r:arg>xpathFuns</r:arg> parameter  of <r:func>getNodeSet</r:func>
as we did for the C code
<r:code>
ll = getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = llfib.ptr))
</r:code>
</para>


<para>
<r:code>
identical(sapply(cc, xmlValue), sapply(ll, xmlValue))
</r:code>
cc and ll are identical if run on the same instance of doc.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title></title>

<para>

<r:code>
B = 30
ll.tm = system.time(replicate(B, getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = llfib.ptr))))
cc.tm = system.time(replicate(B, getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = fib.ptr))  ))
</r:code>
</para>


<para>
<r:code><![CDATA[
fib = function(n) if(n < 2) n else fib(n-1) + fib(n-2)
fib(10) # 55
]]></r:code>

<r:code><![CDATA[
rr = getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = fib))
identical(rr, cc)
]]></r:code>


<r:code>
rr.tm = system.time(replicate(B, getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = fib))  ))
rr.tm/ll.tm
</r:code>
Giving a factor of 158.
</para>

</section>


<section>
<title>Compiling <c:func>fib</c:func> and <c:func>xpathFib</c:func></title>

<para>
The <omg:pkg>RLLVMCompile</omg:pkg> package can handle the simple fib() function
once it is told that the input is an integer (rather than a numeric scalar).
</para>


<para>
There are several ways for us to generate the xpathFib() routine in LLVM.
One is that we create an R function that knows all about XPath and the
available routines, e.g., 
xmlXPathPopBoolean, xmlXPathPopNumber, xmlXPathPopString, xmlXPathPopNodeSet and xmlXPathPopExternal
and xmlXPathReturnNumber, etc.
</para>

<para>
Another approach is that we write the C function as an R function and use
RLLVMCompile to translate that to LLVM.
This is probably simplest as it is most general. However, we need to be able to
provide the types of the parameters and return values of each of the routines we reference.
We can use RCIndex for that.
</para>
<para>
So we can define an R function that mirrors the xpathFib routine:
<r:function><![CDATA[
xpathFib = 
function(ctxt, nargs)
{
   num = xmlXPathPopNumber(ctxt) 
   xmlXPathReturnNumber(ctxt, fib( num ))
}
]]></r:function>  
This calls <c:func>xmlXPathPopNumber</c:func> and <c:func>xmlXPathReturnNumber</c:func>.
So we need the signatures for both of these.
If we can find the signature of these,
then we can (almost) infer the type of xpathFib.
We see the use of ctxt in the call to xmlXPathReturnNumber, so
that defines the type of the ctxt parameter in xpathFib.
The nargs paramter is never used, so we can't determine the type.
However, perhaps we should add a check in the function that nargs == 1 or nargs > 0
and that would allow us to infer the type.
</para>
<para>
We'll see that xmlXPathReturnNumber is a macro that calls valuePush().
That returns an int value. However, our xpathFib routine should return a void.
So we would tell RLLVMCompile to have it return void and not the value from
xmlXPathReturnNumber.
</para>

<para>
To get the type of the parameters,
we read the xpath header files.
We create a simple xpath.c file
<c:code><![CDATA[
#include <libxml/xpath.h>
#include <libxml/xpathInternals.h>
]]>
</c:code>

<r:code>
library(RCIndex)
  # Compute the include directories
cflags = system("xml2-config --cflags", intern = TRUE)
flags = strsplit(cflags, " ")[[1]]
incs = gsub("-I", "", flags[grep("^-I", flags)])
tu = createTU("xpath.c", incs)
rr = getRoutines(tu)
</r:code>


We find the return type of xmlXPathPopNumber
<r:code>
xp = rr$xmlXPathPopNumber
getName(xp$returnType)
</r:code>


Next, we get the type of the ctxt parameter:
<r:code>
cxtTy = getCanonicalType(getType(xp@params[[1]]))
isPointerType(ctxtTy)
</r:code>
Importantly, it is an opaque pointer.
</para>



<para>
To determine the return type of the function,
we would look for the return type of xmlXPathReturnNumber().
This is not listed in the routines.
<r:code>
tu2 = createTU("xpath.c", incs, options = RCIndex:::CXTranslationUnit_DetailedPreprocessingRecord)
</r:code>
<r:code><![CDATA[
k = function() { ans = list(); function(cur, ...) if(getName(cur) == "xmlXPathReturnNumber") ans <<- c(ans, cur)}
zz = k()
tu2 = createTU("xpath.c", incs, options = RCIndex:::CXTranslationUnit_DetailedPreprocessingRecord)
m = environment(zz)$ans[[1]]
toks = getCursorTokens(m)
getParams(toks)
]]></r:code>

So we would replace
<r:code>
xmlXPathReturnNumber(ctxt, fib(num))
</r:code>
with
<r:code>
valuePush(ctxt, xmlXPathNewFloat( fib(num)) )
</r:code>
So we are doing what the pre-processor is doing.

</para>
<para>
Given the nature of the XPath wrapper functions,
it is perhaps simplest to generate the wrapper routine
NOT using RLLVMCompile.
Instead, we'll write a function that takes an R
function and some type information and generates the
wrapper function as an LLVM Function. 


</para>

</section>
<section>
<title></title>

<para>
<r:code>
source("genXPathWrapper.R")
</r:code>
</para>

<para>
<r:code>
library(Rllvm)
m = parseIR("fibOnly.ll")
m2 = clone(m)
xp = genXPathWrapper(m2$fib)

</r:code>
<r:code>
library(XML)
llvmAddSymbol("xmlXPathPopNumber", "xmlXPathNewFloat", "valuePush")
</r:code>

<r:code>
ee = ExecutionEngine(m2)
xp  = getPointerToFunction(m2$xpathfib, ee)@ref
</r:code>

<r:code>
doc = xmlParse("doc.xml")
ll = getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ fib(number(.)) > 10 ]", xpathFuns = list(fib = xp))
</r:code>
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Character Strings</title>


<para>
  Here we write a routine that maps a month number to its name.
  Then we compare the month name to April.
  This is not an intelligent way of doing the XPath query. However, it illustrates
  wrapping a routine that returns a string - <c:type>const char *</c:type>.
</para>

<para>
  Again, we write the routine in C and convert it to IR so that we can skip that part.
  However, we could write an R function such as
<r:function><![CDATA[
monthName = function(num) MonthNames[num]
]]></r:function>
and then translate that to IR very easily.
</para>

<para>
As before, we read the IR and clone the module.  
<r:code>
library(Rllvm)
m = parseIR("fibOnly.ll")
m2 = clone(m)
</r:code>

We generate the XPath wrapper routine in the m2 module
<r:code>
source("genXPathWrapper.R")
mn = genXPathWrapper(m2$monthName)
</r:code>

We load the XML package and its DSO and then register the routines
the module (m2) uses that come from that DSO:
<r:code>
library(XML)
llvmAddSymbol("xmlXPathPopNumber", "xmlXPathNewCString", "valuePush")
</r:code>

We create the execution engine/context and find the address in memory of our
newly created XPath wrapper routineL
<r:code>
ee = ExecutionEngine(m2)
xp  = getPointerToFunction(m2$xpathmonthName, ee)@ref
</r:code>
Finally, we pass the address of the routine via the <r:arg>xpathFuns</r:arg> parameter
and process the <xml:tag>mon</xml:tag> elements in the <xml/> document.
<r:code>
doc = xmlParse("doc2.xml")
ll = getNodeSet(doc, "//mon[ month(number(.)) = 'April' ]", xpathFuns = list(month = xp))
</r:code>

<r:code>
ll
</r:code>
</para>
</section>



<section>
<title>DoubleType log() routine</title>

<para>
We wrote log(double val) return(log(val)) in the C code which is infinitely recursive.
So we we need a name mylog for our implementation of log.
See below for using the built-in log routine directly.
</para>

<para>
<r:code>
library(Rllvm)
m = parseIR("fibOnly.ll")
m2 = clone(m)

source("genXPathWrapper.R")
mn = genXPathWrapper(m2$mylog)

library(XML)
llvmAddSymbol("xmlXPathPopNumber", "xmlXPathNewFloat", "valuePush")

ee = ExecutionEngine(m2)
xp  = getPointerToFunction(m2$xpathmylog, ee)@ref

doc = xmlParse("doc.xml")
ll = getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ log(number(.)) > 3.0 ]", xpathFuns = list(log = xp))
</r:code>
</para>


<section>
<title>Built-in log() Routine</title>
<para>
Here we use the built-in log() function directly.
So create a wrapper to the libc log routine.
<r:code>
library(Rllvm)
m = parseIR("fibOnly.ll")
m2 = clone(m)

source("genXPathWrapper.R")
Function("log", DoubleType, DoubleType, m2)
mn = genXPathWrapper(m2$log)

library(XML)
llvmAddSymbol("xmlXPathPopNumber", "xmlXPathNewFloat", "valuePush", "log")
</r:code>

Note our new function is called xpathlog and not xpathmylog.
However, we can also pass the returned function from genXPathWrapper() directly
<r:code>
ee = ExecutionEngine(m2)
xp  = getPointerToFunction(m2$xpathlog, ee)@ref
xp  = getPointerToFunction(mn, ee)@ref
</r:code>
So we can now use this routine in an XPath query:
<r:code>
doc = xmlParse("doc.xml")
ll = getNodeSet(doc, "//value[ log(number(.)) > 3.0 ]", xpathFuns = list(log = xp))
length(ll)
all(log(as.numeric(sapply(ll, xmlValue))) > 3.0)
table(log(as.numeric(sapply(getNodeSet(doc, "//value"), xmlValue))) > 3.0)
</r:code>
</para>

</section>
</section>


</article>
